A Finding Aid to the Abraham Rattner and Esther Gentle Papers, 1891-1986, in the Archives of American Art AAA.rattabra
Archives of American Art
Shelden Rodman, 1909-
Waverly Root, 1903-1982
Felix Emmanuele Ruvolo, 1912-
Frank Sedlak
Paul Shapiro
Jack Gage Stark, 1882-1950
Barrie Stavis
Ike Stoeffle
Benjamin Ellis Tepper
David Turnbull
Alfredo Valente
Siegfried Wang
Frank C. Watkins (Franklin Chenault), 1894-1972
Allen Weller, 1907-
Bedwell, Bettina, 1889-1947; Biddle, George, 1885-; Boyle, Kay, 1902; Burlin, Paul, 1886-1969; Carton, Norman, 1908-1980; Coates, Robert M. (Robert Myron), 1897-1973; Davis, Stuart, 1892-1964; De Rochemont, Richard; Dehn, Adolf, 1895-1968; Dos Passos, John, 1896-1970; Downtown Gallery (New York, N.Y.); Esther Gentle Reproductions; Gentle, Esther, 1900-; Gonzalez, Xavier, 1898-1993; Griffin, John Howard, 1920-; Guthrie, Ramon, 1896-; Gwathmey, Robert, 1903-1988; Hall, William Weeks, 1894-1958; Hayter, Stanley William, 1901-; Hiler, Hilaire, 1898-1966; Hirsch, Joseph, 1910-; Hirsch, Stefan, 1899-1964; Holty, Carl, 1900-1973; Hélion, Jean, 1904-1987; Kennedy Galleries; Kronberg, Louis, 1872-1965; Lebrun, Rico, 1900-1964; Leepa, Allen, 1919-; Lipchitz, Jacques, 1891-; Ludgin, Earle, 1898-1981; Malcolm, Thalia Westcott, b. 1878; Miller, Henry, 1891-; Miró, Joan, 1893-; Nordfeldt, Bror Julius Olsson, 1878-1955; Paul Rosenberg & Co.; Peake, Channing, 1910-; Poor, Henry Varnum, 1887-1970; Ruvolo, Feliz; Stark, Jack Gage, 1882-1950; Watkins, Franklin Chenault, 1894-1972; Weller, Allen Stuart, 1907-; Art--Study and teaching--France--Paris; Artist couples; Diaries; Interviews; Painters--France--Paris; Painters--New York (State)--New York; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sketches; Works of art
- Biographical Files, 1893-1978, undated; Series 1; (box 1; 0.2 linear ft.)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains official documentation such as birth certificates, visas, and passport applications, in addition to other biographical material such as awards, curriculum vitae, and obituaries.
  - Birth certificate, 1893 (Box 1, Reel 5258)
  - High School Yearbook, 1912 (Box 1, Reel 5258)
  - Student records, 1913-1914 (Box 1, Reel 5258)
  - French visas, 1937-1939; (3 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5258)
  - Guggenheim Memorial Foundation Fellowship Application, 1940 (Box 1, Reel 5258)
  - Selective Service questionnaire, 1942 (Box 1, Reel 5258)
  - Current Biography article, 1948 (Box 1, Reel 5258)
  - Awards, 1947-1974 (Box 1, Reel 5258)
  - Honorary Doctorate, Pratt Institute, commencement program, 1969 (Box 1, Reel 5258)
  - Honorary Doctorate, Michigan State University, certificate, 1977 (Box 1, Reel 5258)
  - Draft of Will, 1948 (Box 1, Reel 5258)
  - Drafts of Will, 1965 (Box 1, Reel 5258)
  - Driving permits, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Reel 5258)
  - Marquis National Biographie notes, 1953 (Box 1, Reel 5258)
  - Religion and Man in Contemporary Art exhibition application, 1957 (Box 1, Reel 5258)
  - Electro Cardiogram, 1958 (Box 1, Reel unfilmed)
  - Curriculum vitae, 1965 (Box 1, Reel 5258)
  - Chronology 1895-1969 (Box 1, Reel 5258)
  - Who's Who In America, 1970 (Box 1, Reel 5258)
  - Passport application, 1973 (Box 1, Reel 5258)
  - Obituaries, 1978 (Box 1, Reel 5258)
  - Biographical notes, undated (Box 1, Reel 5258)
- Interviews with Abraham Rattner, 1957-1975, undated; Series 2; (box 1; 7 folders)
  This series contains transcripts of seven interviews with Rattner which are arranged chronologically and listed by name of interviewer.
  - Kellog Center for Continuing Education, 1957 (Box 1, Reel 5258)
  - Marc Saporta, in French, 1965 (Box 1, Reel 5258)
  - Henry Kraus, 1973 (Box 1, Reel 5258)
  - Chevalier, 1973 (Box 1, Reel 5258)
  - Theodore Enron, 1975 (Box 1, Reel 5258)
  - Allen Leepa, undated (Box 1, Reel 5258)
  - Gene Fenn, undated (Box 1, Reel 5258)
- Correspondence Files, 1933-1978, undated; Series 3; (boxes 1-5; 4.3 linear ft.)
  Chronological correspondence contains letters from family, friends, artists, writers, and gallery owners, as well as a notebook that records correspondents and dates. Many of Rattner's own letters are also included in this series. Major correspondents found in this subseries include: Ramon Guthrie, Richard De Rochemont, Stuart Davis, Robert Gwathmey, Franklin C. Watkins, Carl Holty, Hilaire Hiler, John Dos Passos, Channing Peake, George Biddle, Kay Boyle, Norman Carton, Xavier Gonzalez, Robert Coates, Thalia Wescott Malcolm, Shelden Rodman, and Joseph Hirsch among others.
  Alphabetical correspondence contains letters from friends, associations, colleges and universities soliciting Rattner for teaching positions, as well as a folder entitled "Requests". Rattner's long friendship with the writer Henry Miller is chronicled in this subseries. Additional major correspondents found in this subseries include Artists Equity Association, Kay Boyle, Paul Burlin, Emily Genauer, Weeks Hall, Bill Hayter, Rico LeBrun, Bill Ney, Anais Nin, Henry Varnum Poor, Waverly Root, and Jack Gage Stark. Rattner's letters also may be found here.
  Arrangement note
  Correspondence that is alphabetical by subject is arranged according to Rattner's filing system.
  - Notebook record of correspondence, 1947-1950; (2 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5258)
  - Chronological correspondence, 1933-1942; (12 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5258)
  - Chronological correspondence, 1943-1945, undated; (3 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5259)
  - Chronological correspondence, 1945-1949; (10 folders) (Box 2, Reel 5259)
  - Chronological correspondence, 1949-1963; (15 folders) (Box 2, Reel 5260)
  - Chronological correspondence, 1963-1965; (3 folders) (Box 3, Reel 5260)
  - Chronological Correspondence, 1965-1978; (16 folders) (Box 3, Reel 5261)
  - Harry N. Abrams, Inc., 1970-1975 (Box 3, Reel 5261)
  - Albright Art Gallery, Buffalo, New York, 1952-1953 (Box 3, Reel 5261)
  - American Academy in Rome, 1950-1951 (Box 3, Reel 5261)
  - American Federation of Arts, 1954 (Box 3, Reel 5261)
  - Anti-Defamation League, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Reel 5261)
  - Archives of American Art, 1965-1973 (Box 3, Reel 5261)
  - Art Association of Indianapolis, Indiana, 1954 (Box 3, Reel 5261)
  - Art Director's Club, 1956 (Box 3, Reel 5262)
  - Art Institute of Chicago, 1955-1956 (Box 3, Reel 5262)
  - Artists Equity Association, 1947-1975, undated; (4 folders) (Box 3, Reel 5262)
  - Artists Gallery, 1955 (Box 3, Reel 5262)
  - Art Students League, 1950, 1954 (Box 3, Reel 5262)
  - Associated American Artists, 1968-1971 (Box 3, Reel 5262)
  - Associated Artists of Pittsburgh, 1950-1951 (Box 3, Reel 5262)
  - Atlanta Art Association, 1954-1955 (Box 3, Reel 5262)
  - N. W. Ayer & Son, Inc., 1950-1956 (Box 3, Reel 5262)
  - Baal-Teshuva, Jacob, undated (Box 3, Reel 5262)
  - Ball State Teachers College, 1954 (Box 3, Reel 5262)
  - Barone Gallery, 1955 (Box 3, Reel 5262)
  - Beckett, Samuel, 1973; (negative from photograph of a letter) (Box 3, Reel 5262)
  - Beiber, Carl, 1971 (Box 3, Reel 5262)
  - Belmont, George, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Reel 5262)
  - Beloit College, Beloit, Wisconsin, 1954 (Box 3, Reel 5262)
  - Bergamo Exhibition International, 1950 (Box 3, Reel 5262)
  - Berkeley Health Club, undated (Box 3, Reel 5262)
  - Birmingham Museum of Art, 1953-1954 (Box 3, Reel 5262)
  - Black Mountain College, North Carolina, 1949 (Box 3, Reel 5262)
  - Boston School of the Museum of Fine Arts, 1950 (Box 3, Reel 5262)
  - Boston Art Festival, 1955 (Box 3, Reel 5262)
  - Boston Public Library, 1954-1955 (Box 3, Reel 5262)
  - Bowdoin College, Brunswick, Maine, 1954 (Box 3, Reel 5262)
  - Boxer, Leslie, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Reel 5262)
  - Boyle, Kay, 1973 (Box 3, Reel 5262)
  - Brooklyn Museum, 1954 (Box 3, Reel 5262)
  - Brooklyn Museum Art School, 1948-1949 (Box 3, Reel 5262)
  - Brooklyn Public Library, 1954 (Box 3, Reel 5262)
  - Brussels, 1970 (Box 3, Reel 5262)
  - Burlin, Paul, 1945-1947 (Box 3, Reel 5262)
  - Carnegie Institute, 1946-1949 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Carl, Maurice, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Christ-Janer, Albert, 1967 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Church of Ascension, 1954 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Church Studio, 1956 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Cleveland Museum of Art, 1956 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - College Art Association, 1949-1954 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Columbia University, 1951-1955 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Columus Art League, 1956 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Committee of Religion and Art in America, Inc., 1975 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Contemporary Arts Association, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Corcoran Gallery of Art, 1949, 1953 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Corcoran School of Art, 1951, 1953 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Das, Elsie, 1948-1949 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Des Moines Art Center, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Detroit Institute of Arts, 1954 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Diomaiuto, Gino, 1971 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Dos Passos, John, 1947 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Drake University, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Dundee Designs, 1955 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - East Hampton Art School, 1955-1956 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Albert Einstein School of Medicine, 1953 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Exhibition of Contemporary Engraving International Show, 1950 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Farina, Father Michael, 1975-1976 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Faro, R. Vale, 1946-1947, undated (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Fleischman, Lawrence, 1970, 1974 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Florida State University, 1954, 1956 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Fort Worth Art Center, 1955-1956 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Foundation of Jewish Philanthropies, 1974, 1976 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Frasier, Morris & Co., 1947-1949 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Friends of Ben Shahn, Inc., 1971 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Frothingham, Elizabeth, 1975 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Fulbright International, 1949-1952 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Genauer, Emily, 1965-1974 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Gentle, Esther, 1948-1949 (Box 4, Reel unfilmed)
  - Guild Hall, 1972-1974 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Gwalhney, Robert, undated (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Gwilt-Jolley, Veronica, 1955 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Hall, Weeks, 1941-1948, undated (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Hallmark International Competition, undated (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Harris, Roy, undated (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Hayter, Bill, 1943, 1947, undated (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Herald Tribune, 1969 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Heschel, Abraham, 1969 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Heydenryk, Henri (framer), 1948-1949 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Hiler, Hilaire, 1936-1943 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Holty, Carl Robert, 1939 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Honolulu Art School, 1948-1954 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Huntington Hartford Foundation, 1954 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Income Tax Information, 1945-1947 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - International Design Conference, 1953-1955 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Iowa State Teachers College, 1954 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Israel-Mambush, 1971-1973 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Jewish Theological Seminary of America, 1967-1968 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - King, David, 1971 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Kootz, Samuel, 1943, undated (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Krannert Art Museum, 1964, 1975 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - LeBrun, Rico, 1941-1942, 1952, undated (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Loebl, Schlossman, Bennet & Dart, 1965-1972, undated (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Lost Generation, 1974 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Louis Comfort Tiffany Foundation, 1951 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Louisiana State University, 1949 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Love, Paul, 1972 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Ludgin, Earle, 1952-1978 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - MacDowell Colony, 1953-1954, 1969 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Mayne, Margot, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - McAhnon, Bob, 1939 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1950 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Michigan State University, 1956, 1958, undated (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Midwest College Art Conference, 1960 (Box 4, Reel 5262)
  - Miller, Henry, 1937-1979, undated; (9 folders) (Box 4, Reel 5262-5263)
  - Miller, Lepska, 1946-1947 (Box 4, Reel 5263)
  - Mint Museum, Charlotte, North Carolina, 1951 (Box 4, Reel 5263)
  - Museum of Modern Art, 1944, 1954-1955 (Box 4, Reel 5263)
  - National Academy of Design, 1950, 1954 (Box 4, Reel 5263)
  - National Council on Aging, 1975 (Box 4, Reel 5263)
  - National Institute of Arts and Letters, 1956-1971 (Box 4, Reel 5263)
  - National Council for U.S. Art, 1955 (Box 4, Reel 5263)
  - Neuberger, Mrs. Roy R., [1954] (Box 4, Reel 5263)
  - New Directions, 1945-1977, undated (Box 4, Reel 5263)
  - New School for Social Research, 1947-1949 (Box 4, Reel 5263)
  - New York City Center, 1954 (Box 4, Reel 5263)
  - News Syndicate Co., Inc., 1947 (Box 4, Reel 5263)
  - Ney, Bill, 1940, undated (Box 4, Reel 5263)
  - Nin, Anais, 1975 (Box 4, Reel 5263)
  - Nolan, Sidney, 1958-1960 (Box 4, Reel 5263)
  - Northlight Foundation, 1954 (Box 4, Reel 5263)
  - Pearson, Ralph M., 1954 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts Fellowship, 1955, 1969 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts School, 1956-1956 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Pepsi-Cola Annual Art Competition, 1946-1948 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Philadelphia Museum of Art, 1950 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Piper, Dr. Raymond F., 1947, 1956 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Polymer Medium, [1955] (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Poor, Henry Varnum and Anne, 1939-1940, undated (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Raynal, Maurice, [1951] (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Requests, 1948-1950 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Rochester Memorial Art Gallery, 1956 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Romeike, Henry, Inc., 1946, 1950 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Root, Waverley, 1973-1975 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Rosoff, Noah, 1971-1974 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Rothblatt, Ben, 1956-1957 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Rothenberg, Samuel, 1968 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Royal Society of the Arts, 1971 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Ruvolo, Felix, 1947 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Sachs, William, 1968-1969 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Sag Harbor School, undated (Box 5, Reel unfilmed)
  - St. John's University, Collegeville, Minnestota, 1955-1956 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Salinas, Marcel and Sue, 1971 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Salko, S[amuel], 1955 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Schuster, M. (Simon and Schuster), 1962 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Schwartz, Barry, 1970-1971 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Schwartz, Leonard, 1970 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Sclar, Samuel, 1947-1950 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Sedlak, Frank (copies), undated (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - See, Ingram, 1971 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Septimus, Louis J. & Co., 1951 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Sheets, Millard, 1956 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Shenker, Israel, 1968, 1974 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Silverberg, Nathan, 1970-1975, undated (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Skowhegan School of Painting and Sculpture, 1949-1954 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Smithsonian Institution, 1967-1977 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Smithsonian Institution, James Smisthson Society, 1968, 1976-1977 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Society for Contemporary American Art, Chicago, Illinois, 1948, 1956 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Stark, Jack Gage, 1939-1950, undated (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Stein, Carolyn, 1949 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Strype, Fred C., 1950 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Tel Aviv Museum, 1969-1972, undated (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Temple University, 1953-1954 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Tepper, Ruth, 1975 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Terkel, Studs, 1976 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Townley, Updike and Carter, 1947-1948 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Transworld Art Corporation, 1974 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - Traverse Festival Exhibition of International Contemporary Art, Edinburgh, 1964-1965 (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - UNESCO, [1952] (Box 5, Reel 5263)
  - University of Colorado, Boulder, Colorado, 1948-1949 (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - University of Georgia, Athens, Georgia, 1950 (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - University of Illinois, Urbana, 1949-1954, undated (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - University of Oklahoma, Norman, Oklahoma, 1948 (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - University of Southern California, Los Angeles, California, 1953 (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - University of Texas, Austin, Texas, 1950 (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - University of Washington, Seattle, Washington, 1946-1950 (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - University of Wisconsin/Madison Art Association, 1954 (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - University of Wyoming, Laramie, Wyoming, 1949-1952 (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - Utah State Agricultural College, Logan, Utah, 1956 (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - Vassar College, 1948-1949 (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - Washington University, St. Louis, Missouri, 1949, 1955 (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - Watkins, Franklin C., 1945, undated (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - Weller, Allen, 1955-1971 (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1954 (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - Woman's College of the University of North Carolina, Greensboro, 1954 (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - Women's Campaign for United Jewish Appeal, 1975-1976 (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - Woodstock Art Conference, 1950 (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - Woodstock Artists Association, 1949 (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - Yale University, 1954-1955 (Box 5, Reel 5264)
- Special Projects, 1940-1987; Series 4; (boxes 5-6, ovs 33-35; 1.5 linear ft.)
  These files concentrate on artistic projects that Rattner paid a considerable amount of attention to. The documents are arranged according to project and are in chronological order. They contain correspondence, designs, writings, and notes. Stained-glass is further divided by specific project. Rattner was very involved in the production of Allen Leepa's book entitled Abraham Rattner. Rattner wrote explanations for most illustrations in the book, providing insight for the researcher.
  The series contains a group of files relating to Rattner's trip across the United States with Henry Miller. These include notebooks and notes, writings by Rattner and Miller, correspondence, material relating to exhibitions resulting from the trip, and text for a Rattner/Miller portfolio.
  The file on Allen Leepa's book on Rattner includes notes, lists, drafts of chapters with Rattner's annotations, Rattner's quotes for illustrations, photocopies of illustrations, proofs (incomplete), correspondence, book review.
  - "The Artist Looks at Science," Life Magazine article illustrations, sketches, 1940 (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - U.S.A. trip, notebook 1, [1940] (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - U.S.A. trip, notebook 2, [1941] (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - U.S.A. trip, notebook 3, [1941] (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - U.S.A. trip, explanation of project, undated (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - U.S.A. trip, "When We Were Together," by Rattner, 1944 (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - U.S.A. trip, typescripts of impressions for The Air-Conditioned Nightmare by Miller, 1956, undated (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - U.S.A. trip, Miller's foreword for Rattner's portfolio, 1957 (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - U.S.A. trip, Rattner's notes on portfolio publications, [1972] (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - U.S.A. trip, correspondence for Our America exhibition, 1975-1978 (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - U.S.A. trip, script for panels for Our America exhibition, circa 1975-1978 (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - U.S.A. trip, photocopy of Our America exhibition catalog (see also ov 33 for exhibition poster), 1987 (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - U.S.A. trip, photocopy of Our America exhibition catalog, 1987 (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - U.S.A. trip, Kennedy Gallery exhibition, 1979 (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - U.S.A. trip, photostats and proofs of Rattner's drawings (see ov 34 for drawing proofs for portfolio), undated; (3 folders) (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - U.S.A. trip, photostats of portfolio text, undated (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - U.S.A. trip, "The Other Part" text, 1941, undated (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - Designs for the interior of a Cleveland synagogue, correspondence and notes, 1950 (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - Stained glass, general, undated (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - Stained glass notes, 1953-1955, 1972, undated; (4 folders) (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - Notebook, American Federation of Arts: New Work in Stained Glass, 1952-1953 (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - Stained glass, DeWaters Art Center, Flint Michigan, 1957-1958; (see also ov 35; includes unfilmed blueprint) (Box 5, Reel 5264)
  - Stained glass, Loop Synagogue, Chicago, Illinois, 1957-1966, 1976, undated; (4 folders; includes unfilmed designs, architectural plans) (Box 5, Reel 5264-5265)
  - Stained glass, Loop Synagogue, Chicago, Illinois, 1957-1966, 1976, undated; (9 folders) (Box 6, Reel 5265)
  - Mosaic project for House of Theology, Centerville, Ohio, 1957-1958 (Box 6, Reel 5265)
  - Beggar's Opera, lithographs, 1959-1960, 1970-1972; (includes contract with publisher) (Box 6, Reel 5265)
  - Tapestry design projects, Cleveland and Dallas, 1957, 1962 (Box 6, Reel 5265)
  - Chanukah book illustrations, 1965; (includes a sketch) (Box 6, Reel 5265)
  - The Gallows of Baghdad painting, 1966-1979, undated; (3 folders; includes studio notebook) (Box 6, Reel 5265)
  - Mosaic columns and and tapestries for Fairmont Temple of Anshe Chesed, 1966; (includes designs) (Box 6, Reel 5265)
  - Victory--Jerusalem the Golden painting, 1968 (Box 6, Reel 5265)
  - Abraham Rattner, book by Allen Leepa, 1968-1971, undated; (28 folders) (Box 6, Reel 5265-5266)
  - In The Beginning lithographs, 1971-1973 (Box 6, Reel 5266)
- Joan d'Arc Fresco painted by Paul Gaugin, 1925-1963, undated; Series 5; (box 7, ov 36; 11 folders)
  These files document the discovery, purchase, conservation, and selling process of a fresco painted by Gauguin in 1889. Rattner discovered this fresco in a auberage in 1924 and bought it from the owner. Materials include a dis-mantled book written and illustrated by Rattner, along with photographs that explain the discovery and purchase of the Joan d'Arc fresco, correspondence, certificate of authentication, legal documents, the conservation technical record and notes.
  - Purchase Receipt, 1925 (Box 7, Reel 5266)
  - Correspondence, 1926-1965; (2 folders) (Box 7, Reel 5266)
  - Statement of authenticity, 1928 (Box 7, Reel 5266)
  - Legal and other documents (see also ov 36), 1928, 1930, 1949 (Box 7, Reel 5266)
  - Press release on sale, [1950s] (Box 7, Reel 5266)
  - Conservation technical record, 1956 (Box 7, Reel 5266)
  - Notes, undated (Box 7, Reel 5266)
  - Draft of narrative for Rattner's fresco book, undated (Box 7, Reel 5266)
  - Business receipts (Box 7, Reel unfilmed)
  - Photostats, undated (Box 7, Reel unfilmed)
- Gallery Files, 1942-1975; Series 6; (boxes 7-8; 1.5 linear ft.)
  These files relay Rattner's relationships with the galleries that represented his art work. The papers include correspondence, inventories, purchase slips, and Rattner's records and notes regarding the Rosenberg Gallery, the Downtown Gallery, the Kennedy Galleries and the Circle Gallery.
  - Rosenberg Gallery, 1942-1957; (13 folders) (Box 7, Reel 5266)
  - Downtown Gallery, 1956-1968; (14 folders) (Box 7, Reel 5266-5267)
  - Kennedy Galleries, 1968-1975; (2 folders) (Box 7, Reel 5267)
  - Circle Gallery, Ltd., 1971-1975 (Box 7, Reel 5267)
  - Krannert Art Museum, 1963 (Box 7, Reel 5267)
  - Downtown Gallery Inventory Cards for Artwork, 1943-1967, undated (Box 8 (hol), Reel 5267)
- Exhibition Files, 1963-1978; Series 7; (boxes 7, 9; 9 folders)
  This series contains files that represent exhibitions at galleries that did not represent Rattner, and special exhibitions at museums or festivals.
  - Krannert Art Museum, 1963 (Box 7, Reel 5267)
  - Edinburgh International Festival, 1964 (Box 7, Reel 5267)
  - Coard Gallery, 1964-1965, 1968-1969 (Box 7, Reel 5267)
  - Numa Gallery, 1974 (Box 9, Reel 5267)
  - Camhi Galleries, 1974 (Box 9, Reel 5267-5268)
  - Lowe Art Museum, 1974 (Box 9, Reel 5268)
  - Corcoran Gallery of Art, 1974 (Box 9, Reel 5268)
  - The Jewish Museum, 1974-1975 (Box 9, Reel 5268)
  - John R. and Eleanor R. Mitchell Foundation, 1978 (Box 9, Reel 5268)
- Writings, 1940-1972, undated; Series 8; (box 9; 0.9 linear ft.)
  This series contains some of Rattner's writings. A prolific writer, Rattner often wrote down his thoughts and his concerns. He wrote poetry, articles for publication, but primarily he wrote about art.
  - Poems, 1940, undated (Box 9, Reel 5268)
  - "An American From Paris," for Magazine of Art, [1945] (Box 9, Reel 5268)
  - Miscellaneous, 1946, undated (Box 9, Reel 5268)